Guide to the Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad Company Records, 1860-1999 AIS.1982.23
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad, 1860-1999; VII.
  - Engineering, 1850-1944; 1.
    - Official documents of Lake Erie and Ohio River Canal Project, and Beaver River/Mahoning Canal; includes correspondence, reports, radio, magazines, U.S. Congressional Committee reports; Upper Ohio Vallery Assoc., Board of Army Engineers for Rivers & Harbors; protests and resolutions; Ohio Railroad Assoc., chambers of commerce outside of Pittsburgh; opponents--West Branch, 1935-1963 (Box 363a-363b)
    - Bound newspaper clippings of the Ohio River and Lake Erie Canal Project, 1967-1969 (Box 364)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1965-1967 (Box 366-367)
    - Reports of coal reserves, recoverable coal at mines, freight survey (1931-34); Ashtabula and Shenango trackage rights agreements, contracts, and reports (1976-84); Union mediation agreements (90s), 1931-44; 1976-91 (Box 370)
    - Burelles clippings on Lake Erie and Ohio River canal, 1962-1965 (Box 375)
    - Burelles clippings on Lake Erie and Ohio River Canal, 1960s (Box 378)
    - Train movement reports (1973-77), radio and wireless communication (1987); bow train, cabin, and caboose, 1973-1987 (Box 382)
    - Correspondence concerning Steel Car Shop of McKees Rocks; route at Presto, PA; track, bridge, and grade crossing construction agreements; Neville Island road crossings, 1924-1961 (Box 387)
    - Chief Engineer correspondence to and from Pittsburgh & Lake Erie regarding US government dam construction proposal, 1913-1940 (Box 394b)
    - Correspondence and notices concerning Interstate Commerce Commission; signals inspections; sidetrack agreements; lease agreements; protection of grade crossings within Pittsburgh city limits; employee matters; PC&Y; property issues, 1902-1960 (Box 398a-398b)
    - Correspondence on repairs to tracks (1970s); North Star transfer station operations (1950s); proposed dock transfer plant in Corona (1932-55); issues dealing with various crossings and properties (1933-46), 1933-1976 (Box 403)
    - Chief Engineer's signed agreements: leases, licenses, etc., 1921-1956 (Box 404)
    - Chief Engineer's files: Upper Ohio River Valley Project; St. Lawrence Seaway; large bound report (Railroad Committee for the Study of Transportation--Subcommittee on Water Transport Assoc. of American Railroads--Transportation on the Mississippi River System) and U.S. Congressional correspondence, 1941-1950 (Box 405)
    - Engineering issues pertaining to PC&Y and McKeesport station and Neville Island freight, 1933-1949 (Box 406)
    - Correspondence regarding land agreements; sidetrack agreements; McKees Rocks; various companies; right of way, 1902-1960 (Box 407a)
    - Correspondence concerning regarding land and sidetrack agreements; McKees Rocks; right of way; harbor lines; Convention of the National Rivers & Harbors Congress; Norway Furnace Trestle and Tracks; sidetrack agreements; retaining walls at Port Perry; Scott Haven Yard; proposed new bridge over Youghiogheny River at McKeesport; elevators, Annex Building, Pittsburgh, 1914-1957 (Box 407b)
    - Clearances; crossings at New Castle; property leases; harbor lines, 1914-1957 (Box 407c)
    - Correspondence with PC&Y; sidetrack agreements; lease agreements; grade crossings; properties; National Industrial Recovery Act; accident report, 1910-1940 (Box 408a)
    - Reports of material removed and applied to locomotives; locomotive final reports; locomotives formerly of Conrail, 1940-1987 (Box 408b)
    - Correspondence concerning Neville Island bridges; track elevations at McKees Rocks; National Tube Company, 1910-1945 (Box 409b)
    - Train accident reports (1970s) from the office of the Chief Engineer; correspondence concerning Barret Co tracks; IRS records (1915-46); issues concerning Thorn Run Bridge, 1915-1970 (Box 410)
    - Correspondence and papers concerning construction and maintenance from department of engineering - East Youngstown Turntable, Hazelton Overhead Bridge, Vernacular Bridge, P&LE tracks, Youngstown Sheet and Tube Bridge, 1930-1940 (Box 412)
    - Railroad and highway intersections; sidetrack agreements; right of way; Connellsville Station improvements; Connellsville Station in connection with Western Maryland, 1905-1948 (Box 413)
    - Certificates of insurance; elevator construction at main terminal; construction of Monongahela River Bridge; maintenance and construction of terminal building roof, 1937-1952 (Box 414)
    - Association of American Railroads operations and maintenance; department of mechanics, 1955-1988 (Box 417)
    - Track construction, installations, maintenance; property issues; building construction along tracks, 1926-1940 (Box 418-419)
    - Company vehicles and insurance of, freight maintenance, employee training, accounting, employee bulletin, 1970-1980 (Box 420)
    - Repair, maintenance, and construction pertaining to Monongahela River Bridge; various track and maintenance repairs, property issues, 1911-1941 (Box 422)
    - Construction of Blue Bridge at Freeport; main passenger terminal in Pittsburgh to compete with Pennsylvania Railroad originals, blueprints, and expansions (1904-44), numerous projects of Chief Engineer, 1899-1904 (Box 423)
    - Correspondence concerning Flood Committee; sidetracks; maintenance and repair of diesel locomotives; study of Montour Railroad coal movements; joint facilities; flat car conversion design; centralized crew dispatching; cost analyses; Detroit-Edison train; hot slab trains; Aliquippa & Southern Railroad, 1897-1973 (Box 424)
    - Right of way; grade crossings; Anderson Road station; bridge repairs; highway construction; sidings; drainage at Blacks Run; land leases; agreement with other railroads, 1905-1965 (Box 425)
    - Signal failures and inspections; various improvements to Beaver Falls area; tracks at New Castle; property and automobile damages; land leases; company agreements; sidetracks; right of way, 1900-1960 (Box 426)
    - Correspondence regarding U.S. Geological Survey Maps; siding agreement; operation and maintenance of Youngstown, OH YMCA; grade crossings; contracts and leases, 1900-1971 (Box 427)
    - Correspondence relating to authorization of Ferrona Branch; elimination of grade crossings; defective rails; car repairs; sidings in Coraopolis and Johnstown; Woodlawn track scales; rail tests; highway crossings; inspections of pressure vessels, 1910-1956 (Box 428)
    - Construction of new Riverton yard office; U.S. Senate bills; Aliquippa - Colona slag track; issues of Pittsburgh Coal Co.; sidetrack agreements; Crow and Hog Island affairs, 1902-1950S (Box 429)
    - Change of highways; right of ways; property leases; pollution of streams in Allegheny County; various agreements and contracts; shop buildings at Davis Island Repair Yard, 1905-1948 (Box 430)
    - Sidetrack agreements; regulations of Destruction of Records of Steam Railroads and McKees Rocks storage; sidings; pymatuning and draining of swamp; YMCA facilities; widening of East Carson Street; statistics of Youngstown, Oh YMCA, 1901-1958 (Box 431)
    - Recapitulation of engine hours in East Youngstown District; yardmaster dismissals; statements of trackage, cars handled through various yards, car, engine, and caboose mileage; weight and motion scales; Fourth Avenue Project in McKeesport; yardmaster promotions; matters of Lake Erie & Ohio River Canal; memberships in organizations, 1966-1992 (Box 433)
    - Personal Injuries; company vehicles; repairs to and information on freight equipment, 1969-1987 (Box 434)
    - Photocopies of aerial photographs of Pennsylvania Railroad Miracle Run and Brave to Waynesburg, 1966 (Box 436a)
    - Assortment of small ledgers containing field notes, final cross sections, anchoring records, field grades, excavation quantities, etc., of Waynesburg Southern Railroad, 1966-1968 (Box 436b)
    - Electrical requisitions of Mechanical Department; Arbitration Committee minutes and decisions; purchase orders; freight car inventories; Association of American Railroad Manual of Standards and Practices; AAR special reports; vehicles file; card index of railroads; gas receipts, 1980-1990 (Box 438)
    - Water pipelines and construction blueprints; worker payrolls and estimates of expenses, 1914-1946 (Box 439)
    - Superintendent agreements (regarding sidetracks, wages, etc); car records; J&L Steel contract on equipment transfer services; railroad company agreements; studies of billing, switching, and future procedures; various bills; changes in operating facilities at East Youngstown, Oh.; car sales records; contracts with PC&Y, 1939-1983 (Box 440a)
    - Vacuum cleaners; boilers; elevators; weigh stations; equipment tests; lubrication; engineering; machinery, 1976 (Box 449)
    - Visual and hearing exams; Metals Recycling; car cleaning services; inspections; Intra-Industry Claims Agreement; Track Torpedoes specifications and use; Fire and Trainmen Exams; expense accounts; Mechanized Info System; medical exams, 1926-1989 (Box 450)
    - Equipment and appliance catalogs, service and installation manuals, instruction diagrams for equipment installation, 1952-1970 (Box 453)
    - Ohio and Pennsylvania new legislation concerning P B&O's use of tracks-McKeesport to Port Vue; U.S. Army Corps of Engineers notice; Norway trestle and track, sidings; grade crossings and right of way with Lake Erie Limestone Co.; agreements with Republic Steel Company and Mahoning State Line Railroad; sale of land and tracks at New Castle, PA; right of way and power wire crossings, 1923-1955 (Box 454a-454c)
    - Comprehensive compilation of official reports (NGO and government) concerning all waterway projects; emphasis on Ohio River and Lake Erie Canal project, 1921-1965 (Box 468a-468b)
    - TWU Agreements and working agreements; Machinery & Airbrakes exam series; 1990 Joint Inspection--B&LE and P seniority rosters; mechanical dept. locomotives, College, PA (1981); engineering mileage chart logs, 1967-1990 (Box 469)
    - Office of industrial engineering operations; iron ore movements; hopper and gondola studies; correspondence concerning Montour Junction auto ramp; Mahoning State Line Railroad study; Dravo Stone proposal, 1968-1980 (Box 476)
    - Correspondence of Chief Mechanical Officers regarding wheel gauges, welding, Magnaflux program, tools and machinery, air brake testing devices, wheel truing machine, contracts and agreements, Wisconsin electric train, Norfolk Southern track acquisition, 1904-1986 (Box 478)
    - Reports to the office of Chief Engineer from the American Railway Association, Interstate Commerce Commission, Pennsylvania Railroad Association, Eastern Railway Association, General Managers Association; information regarding industrial supplies and equipment; PC&Y Employee medical reports, 1960-1991 (Box 488)
    - Car Department cards of out of service employees prior to 1950, 1880s-1950 (Box 496)
    - Injury and illness reports and statements (1977-92); authorized positions (1984-86); freight car repairs and mechanical department requests for appropriation (1986-89); sale of cars to Chessie system (1986-89); pollution notices (1981-86); Mass Transit Clean Air Act (1974); caboose safety complaints (1968-85); power plants (1963-79); electricity (1968-86); AAR committees, correspondence and reports (1979-91); employee travel and business expenses (1985-92); utility contracts and agreements, 1963-1991 (Box 512)
    - Tread temperature tests (1966); notices (1955-67); sidetrack agreements; documents and plans for rebuilding of caboose; construction plans for Neville Island (1920s); sand cars, track construction Robinson (1940s); Woodland Passenger Station and Subway construction (1909-11), 1920-1980 (Box 514)
    - Cars under obligation, gondola end modification; paperwork, pamphlets, catalogs, and instructions for various equipment and parts, 1976-1989 (Box 515)
    - Matters of importance to Mechanical Engineer Dept. including: Wheel Truing Machine plans; information on Ready-Power Electrical Industrial Truck; locomotive speed indicators and recorders; locomotive brake equipment; locomotive combustion catalyst; D.I. Gantry Crane; various equipment blueprints, track extension plans for Struthers, Oh.; equipment blueprints, 1952-1980 (Box 520a-520b)
    - Dept. of Transportation Training Catalog (1985); other manuals and guides to machinery and procedure; GM Replacement Parts Catalog, Master Parts Catalog; PC- Conrail Standard Maintenance Regulations for Locomotives; locomotive service manual; P&LE Annual Reports (1963-78); Pocket List of Railroad Officials (1989), 1963-1989 (Box 521a-521b)
    - The Public Service Company Law (1925); P&LE Annual Report to Railroad Commission of Ohio (1906); Transportation Law booklet (1960); Rail Planning Procedures Report (1975); 1920s engineer's field books; contracts and agreements between Montour Railroad and other companies; Montour Railroad maintenance reports; general notices from 1991-92, 1906-1992 (Box 522)
    - Chief Engineer's Office equipment and purchase orders, employee age limits; publication information; Youngstown & Southern Railroad Transfer Contract; physical requirements; matters of signals, transportation, and storage; test equipment; microfiches of interchange, 1932-1989 (Box 524)
    - Department of Highways Construction agreements; West End Bridge construction; railroad repairs and construction; project estimates; construction contracts; personal injuries (1981); locomotive construction; McKees Rocks construction, 1930-1950; 1981 (Box 525)
    - Vehicle, machine, and rail equipment brochures; instruction manuals, 1940-1970 (Box 531a)
    - Locomotive school study books and review questions; annual proceedings for various rail associations; port authority commuter rail study; authority for expenditure of Y&S Railway, AAR bulletins concerning claim work; "facts about featherbedding;" Montour expense book (1960); Montour balance sheets (1921-23); annual reports of P&LE, Mahoning, Beaver & Ellwood (1920s), 1940-1970 (Box 531b)
    - Consolidated Rail Corporation Bulletins; flat car improvements, 1980-1992 (Box 531c)
    - Chief Engineer's CL-1 reports; ICC Plans on Abandonment; correspondence with Dept. of Defense; purchase of power; bridge repair program; dept. of commerce & labor - permit applications; OSHA; EPA regulations; dept. of transportation records; Transportation Research Board; rates of pay, 1949-1989 (Box 535)
    - Personal injury summary cards of Montour Railroad employees; LE&E records book; notes on cross sections; LE&E and PL&E crossing agreements, 1922-1965 (Box 540)
    - Duquesne Light construction agreements, "new and relayer rail" status reports, maintenance reports; request for authority; 1956 budget; proposed exterior to central warehouse and annex building, 1940-1959 (Box 541)
    - Reports concerning cars (inspections, delays, maintenance); track routes and maintenance, 1979-1988 (Box 542a)
    - Bulletins and general notices concerning cargo, cars, shipment instructions, transferred loads; correspondence regarding claims and "safety first", 1979 (Box 544a)
    - Trackage and interchange agreements; joint-use agreement between P&LE and New York Central Railroad; agreements with Youngstown rail yard; 1977 investigation into incorrect handling of car, 1928-1989 (Box 545b)
    - Movement of cars; car inventory; coal; janitorial; office supplies; time claims; sidetrack agreements; cargo, careful handling, 1973 (Box 546b)
    - Locomotives: purchased, sold, retired, inspections, maintenance; locomotive department shop orders; freight cars: owned, sold, maintenance, leased; passenger cars, 1966-1984 (Box 548a-548b)
    - Locomotives: purchased, sold, retired, inspections, maintenance; gondolas; General Electric equipment installation instructions and diagrams, 1970-1984 (Box 549a)
    - Equipment and parts sales brochures, equipment and part installation instructions and manuals with diagrams, 1970-1984 (Box 549b)
    - Locomotives: bought, sold, retired, inspections, maintenance; freight car inventory and leases, 1950-1971 (Box 550a-550b)
    - Catalogs and information for various railway parts manufacturers (i.e. GE, Portec, Stanrail); freight car ownership logs, 1978-1986 (Box 551)
    - Sales orders; equipment maintenance monthly reports; shipping notices of cars sold; light weighs; car acceptance certificates; car leases, 1974-1986 (Box 552b)
    - Blueprints, schematics, pamphlets, and correspondence pertaining to equipment and systems for trains and buildings, 1950s-1980s (Box 553a-556b)
    - Car file individual updates; bundles of daily report of employees working punitive times, 1986-1988 (Box 557)
    - Monthly safety meeting; accident reports, lost time, handwritten call directory file book (R.I.Z.), benefits, monthly time book ledger, 1957-1990 (Box 559)
    - Car reports and records of time, cars not suitable for service list, maintenance inspections for buildings etc., 1985-1992 (Box 560)
    - Documents of planning for a Passenger Station at Woodlawn, PA (with correspondence, time estimates, materials inventories, general estimates, blueprints, cost analyses, etc., mostly concerning heating), 1917-1919 (Oversize 578)
    - Inventories of furniture and equipment; heating system valuations, 1913-1920 (Oversize 579)
    - Index of gondola cars-retirement, sale, rebuilding: 100 to 2999 and 3000 to 4999, 1945-1985 (File-cabinet 586)
    - Index of gondola cars-retirement, sale, rebuilding: 35000 to 36499 and 39000 to 40999, 1945-1986 (File-cabinet 587)
    - Reports of initial or number changes; general repair record, 1980s-1990s (File-cabinet 588)
    - Index of auto, truck, locomotives, company work cars, and active leased cars, 1940-1990 (File-cabinet 589)
    - Index of gondola cars-retirement, sale, rebuilding: 73000 to 80299 and 80500 to 20450, 1940-1990 (File-cabinet 590)
    - Index of gondola cars-retirement, sale, rebuilding: 5000 to 2499 and 9000 to 10999, 1949-1990 (File-cabinet 591)
    - Index of gondola cars-retirement, sale, rebuilding: 67000 to 69999 and 70000 to 72999, 1957-1990 (File-cabinet 592)
    - Index of gondola cars-retirement, sale, rebuilding: 11000 to 12999 and 13000 to 17599, 1941-1990 (File-cabinet 593)
    - Index of gondola cars-retirement, sale, rebuilding: 62500 to 63699 and 63700 to 64869, 1957-1990 (File-cabinet 594)
    - Index of gondola cars-retirement, sale, rebuilding: 50000 to 51999 and 60000 to 62499, 1950-1990 (File-cabinet 595)
    - Index of gondola cars-retirement, sale, rebuilding: 41000 to 42249 and 43000 to 49499, 1940-1990 (File-cabinet 596)
    - Index of gondola cars-retirement, sale, rebuilding: 18000 to 19199 and 20000 to 24549, 1949-1990 (File-cabinet 597)
    - Blank Cards Description; Retired Company Work Cars, 1888-1990s (File-cabinet 598)
    - Index of gondola cars-retirement, sale, rebuilding: 24550 to 30499 and 30500 to 32699, 1949-1986 (File-cabinet 599)
  - Financial, 1850-1994; 2.
    These records relate to leases, loans, and accounts with other companies, railroads, or banks; payment or receipt of bills, equipment, and services; railroad valuations; budgets; and tax documents.
    - Purchase of land documents, 1910-1920 (Box 1)
    - Tax Assessment Montour Railroad (1946-50), material proposals for equipment (1966), inspections and permits (1970), other tax documents and audits, 1940-1970 (Box 3)
    - Financial statements, 1979-1988 (Box 19)
    - Board of directors meeting minutes, Finance Committee Documents, 1980s (Box 23)
    - Stock information, Lease Information (Station Square), P&LE real estate dept., 1970s (Box 32)
    - Freight Overcharge financials, Late 1980s - 1990s (Box 132)
    - Acquisition of capital stock of P&LE from Penn Central, Financing Acquisition under Credit Agreement through First National Bank of Boston, 1979 (Box 133)
    - Pittsburgh and Lake Erie Properties (documents concerning property buying and selling, etc), Pittsburgh and Lake Erie Properties (files concerning selling off of land holdings, Engineering Files (Pittsburgh Coal company, agreements), 1912 and 1993 (Box 140)
    - Leases, tax assessments, requisitions, Pittsburgh Coal royalty reports, agreements to leave coal in place, 1960s (Box 177)
    - Expense reports, track change proposals, and correspondence between PL&E and Baltimore & Ohio Railroad on track use, 1940s (Box 285b)
    - Tax Return Information, Gas Meter Readings, Automobile Insurance Records for Montour Railroad Company, Correspondence concerning scale tests, crossing gates, 1931-1985 (Box 326)
    - Early American Express delivery ledgers, reports of operations account, balance sheets, general finance plans, 1897-1900, 1983 (Box 357)
    - Banking records (1987); state and federal taxes, 1956-1958 (Box 372)
    - Check invoices; company work vehicles; gas and steel corporations, 1980-1990 (Box 443)
    - 'Pink Sheets' of Car Department by H.C. Christie; reports of Examination of MCRR and PC&Y; bound operation reports, income accounts, and general balance sheets, 1936-1985 (Box 444a)
    - Bound reports of operations, general balance sheets, and expenditure statements; Montour changes in equipment (1960-66); Carrier's Review of and comments concerning reports for property of PC&Y, 1920-1966 (Box 444b)
    - Paperwork concerning stocks and investments, 1977-1985 (Box 457)
    - Finance; account book (1980s); Chief Engineers' office files on The Nation Supply Co, formerly Union Tool Company, Taulor Forge and Pipe Works, inc. (1910-46), photographs; PC&Y Railroad file on Scott Twp, 1910-1980s (Box 464)
    - Equipment and service orders and requests; bills; estimates; blanket authorizations and authority for expenditure; accident reports; powerhouse reports, 1974-1986 (Box 472)
    - Closing of monthly accounting reports; budgetary procedures for improvements; TWU agreement on meal allowances; responsibility accounting system; monthly forecast statement from auditor and internal audits; bad order reports; Interstate Commerce Commission accounting matters; Controller's bulletins, 1966-1990 (Box 480)
    - Working, e.g., functioning contracts for lien agreements, lease, and loan with various companies and banks, 1939-1969 (Box 503)
    - Legal dept. agreements, contracts, leases, General Electric, local Delaware court case (Bertram Field v. Henry G. Allym, Jr. et al -class action claim); Coal Ventures inc., pre-acquisitions meetings and reports; Mellon Branch account activity, 1978-1993 (Box 505)
    - Injury and illness reports and statements (1977-92); authorized positions (1984-86); freight car repairs and mechanical department requests for appropriation (1986-89); sale of cars to Chessie system (1986-89); pollution notices (1981-86); Mass Transit Clean Air Act (1974); caboose safety complaints (1968-85); power plants (1963-79); electricity (1968-86); AAR committees, correspondence and reports (1979-91); employee travel and business expenses (1985-92); utility contracts and agreements, 1963-1991 (Box 512)
    - R.F.A. and A.F.E. Instructions and Budget Procedures; information and correspondence concerning budgeting for hot water boiling, conditioning systems, furnace, water softener, etc., 1959-1972 (Box 518a)
    - Information and correspondence concerning budgeting for hot water boiling, conditioning systems, furnace, water softener, etc; Consol Coal railroad spur; equipment sales exchange, 1965-1981 (Box 518b)
    - Working Papers; Audit Committee Reports; stock options acquisitions; pension committee and plans; interlocking directorates; stock option or stock purchase plans; reports of holdings; executive committee resolution, 1956-1990 (Box 523)
    - Annual reports, financial statements for PLECO Inc. and subsidiaries; valuation book; locomotive replacement report; field notes; 'Pink Sheet' book, 1880s-1990 (Box 529a)